It's בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we start today on מ' עמוד ב'.
Mem amud bet. Today's דף Daf is מ"א, Mem alef, but we
are an עמוד Amud behind, but it's actually a pretty quick דף,
Daf, so let's see how well we can do here. And we
start on the משנה, Mishnah, we're going through the different parts of
the animals which are a מום Mum and which are not. So
we pick up on the משנה, Mishnah, first
משנה Mishnah מ' עמוד ב'. Mem amud bet. אוזן הגדי הייתה כפולה,
Ozen hagedi hayeta kfula, so there's a case where the ear of
a deer was doubled over. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara exactly
or whatever what that exactly means. אמרו חכמים בזמן שהוא עצם אחד
מום, Amru chachamim bizman shehu etzem echad mum, if it's one bone,
now an ear doesn't have a bone, so רש"י Rashi says it
means like the cartilage. If it's basically the cartilage folded over and
that causes the ear to fold over, then that's a blemish. בזמן
שאין בו עצם, Bizman she'ein bo etzem, now or there's a different
גרסא Girsa here, either our משנה Mishnah says there is no cartilage
in it, or the other one is ואם אינו עצם אחד, Ve'im
eino etzem echad, if it's not one cartilage but two separate cartilages,
like רש"י Rashi would say rather than a folded over ear but
essentially a separate flap protruding out, then אינו מום, Eino mum, it's
not a blemish. Now what's the difference? I mean, either way it
looks pretty bad, and actually if it's one cartilage folded over, you
might think it's less abnormal than actually a totally separate cartilage. So
if you have אין בו עצם, Ein bo etzem, no cartilage at
all, then you could say maybe we just view it more like
as a flap of skin and it's not as big of a
deal. But for once רש"י Rashi actually says here
טעמא לא איפרש, Ta'ama lo isparish, the four lines down of the
wide lines of the middle of the line, he says I don't
really get what the difference here is. So he says, but he
says it's at least not as bad as an extra leg because
it's not as visible.
It shows goes רש"י. Rashi.
But exactly, but I think that that expresses the general challenge we've
been having in this פרק, Perek, which is is that there's a
lot of rules but not a lot of like cases but not
a lot of rules. One minute. רבי חנינא בן גמליאל אומר, Rabbi
Chanina ben Gamliel omer, Rabbi Gamliel says זנב הגדי שהוא דומה לשל
חזיר, Zanav hagedi shehu domeh leshel chazir, if you have a tail
of a goat that is similar to that of a pig, ושאין
בו שלוש חוליות, Veshe'ein bo shalosh chulyot, and probably should be or,
not and, or doesn't have three vertebrae, then הרי זה מום, Harei
zeh mum, that is a blemish. Again, that would be an unusual
form for the
visible enough and unusual enough for the tail of a goat. Yes.
So if we were to start bring קרבנות, Korbanot, how are we
going to figure these things out? You can't bring קרבן Korban with
them.
There you go. So that's why when we when we figure out
everything else about bringing קרבן, Korban, like exactly where the place of
the קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim is and all of that, hopefully we
can also help restore some of these traditions.
Well, I read that there are people who want to bring back
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even
today because
we can bring it
when everybody's טמא, Tamei, but how can we?
Well, if it has absolutely nothing unusual about it, I mean these
are only questions if it has something unusual and how unusual does
it have to be? Right, if you have something that have nothing
unusual about it, that wouldn't be a problem. But you know, you
can join ישיבת עטרת כהנים Yeshivat Ateret Kohanim and try to, you
know, and try to recapture all of this. But it is, but
look, there's very little בבלי Bavli on it as we've seen. The
גמרא Gemara focuses its discussion on more the things that it, you
know,
has better tradition about than on these things. And, you know, so
right, and there's no ירושלמי Yerushalmi because in general there's no ירושלמי
Yerushalmi about, you know, right, about these things. So, yeah, so I
don't know. All right, let's keep on going. Anyways, see the גמרא,
Gemara, I'm sorry, I just lost the focus a bit, one second.
Why would there why was there no ירושלמי? Yerushalmi?
Well, that's a question whether there was ירושלמי Yerushalmi written on קדשים
Kodashim or not, but we just lost it. The רמב"ם Rambam says
in his הקדמה Hakdama to פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayot that there is
a ירושלמי Yerushalmi קדשים, Kodashim, but nobody has ever had it or
had a manuscript of it even. And then about a hundred years
ago, somebody quote unquote discovered a ירושלמי Yerushalmi קדשים Kodashim and used
it to answer like hundreds of problematic רמב"םs, Rambam and of course
it was discovered to be a forgery. So,
anyway, so let's move on. But so the גמרא Gemara says, the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, it is a
good question, right? You would think of all of the things the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi would want to discuss the, you know, קדשים, Kodashim, but
maybe it was safer for them to discuss it in בבל Bavel
and in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you know, because, you know, because
it was like a little too close for comfort there. Anyway, it's
interesting to think about that. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, פיו בלום ורגליו מבולמות. Piv balum veraglav mevulamot.
So if the mouth or the legs are בלום, Balum, what does
that mean? רש"י Rashi has two explanations. One is that it means
that basically they are they're like very narrow, they're not their normal
width. The other is the opposite, it means like blown up, puffed
up, swollen, right, exactly. I'll go with the swollen explanation because it's
easier to explain. Anyway, if it's מחמת הרוח, Machmat haruach, if it
is as a result of, there's a question also what the גרסא
Girsa is, רווח Revach or רוח, Ruach, if it's because of wind,
like some type of a nature, you know, natural cause, like infection
or something of that nature, אינו מום, Eino mum, it's not a
blemish. מחמת העצם, Machmat ha'etzem, if it's that there's the bone is
particularly thick or, you know, and it's deformed actually that way, then
הרי זה מום, Harei zeh mum, then it is. Actually some have
the גרסא Girsa of מחמת עצמו Machmat atzmo as opposed to מחמת
הרוח. Machmat haruach. not etzem not bone but it's a natural that
it's natural, it's naturally deformed that way. אזנו כפולות ozno kefulot if
its if its ears are are doubled בחס חצות be-chas chatzut a
question also גירסא girsa
but anyway it means in the cartilage אחת הרי זה מום achat
harei zeh mum in one it's a מום mum בשתי חס חסיות
bishtei chas chasiyot if it's two separate cartilages אינו מום eino mum
it's not and again that's very bizarre because you would think that
that certainly a deformity. So this is where רש"י Rashi says I
don't know what the reason is. All right, רבן גמליאל אמר Rabban
Gamliel amar now we're going to get to area that's a little
easier to discuss. זנב הגדי שהוא דומה לשל חזיר zenav ha-gedi she-hu
domeh le-shel chazir if the goat's tail is like that of a
pig. אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa לא תימא דקטינא lo teima
de-katina not doesn't only mean that it's small like a pig, a
pig has a very small short tail, אלא דכריכא אף אגב דאלימא
ela de-kericha af agav de-alima
even if it's its normal sort of thickness or size, if it's
rounded then it's that's enough like a pig. Now what does rounded
mean? So רש"י Rashi says that's what I assumed it meant like
it's curled. Right, that's exactly what I assumed. Right, right, that's exactly
what I assumed. רש"י Rashi says what it also means
is that a pig the you know the circumference of the tail
is more circular than that of other animals where the circumference is
more oblong. So that's way רש"י Rashi has it, but I also
I assumed it meant curled. Okay, now we go on. או שאין
בו שלוש חוליות. o she-ein bo shalosh chulyot.
Okay, or if it it does not have three vertebrae. So אמר
רב הונא amar Rav Huna בגדי שתיים הרי זה מום be-gedi shtayim
harei zeh mum even though it says that it needs to have
three vertebrae, here's really the story, if it's a goat then if
it has two well two vertebrae it's a מום, mum, שלוש אינו
מום shalosh eino mum three is not a blemish. That's that's a
minimum amount of vertebrae. בטלה be-taleh by a sheep it's one more.
שלוש הרי זה מום shalosh harei zeh mum three is already too
abnormal. ארבע אינו מום arba eino mum four is already within the
range of of normality and that's okay. Four vertebrae. מיתיבי meitivei I'll
ask you, we have a ברייתא baraita that says the that says
it's one degree more more strict. בגדי אחת הרי זה מום be-gedi
achat harei zeh mum by a goat only one vertebra is a
מום. mum. שתיים אינו מום shtayim eino mum two is already normal
enough. בטלה שתיים הרי זה מום be-taleh shtayim harei zeh mum by
a sheep it's two is a problem or a מום mum actually.
It's good, but it helps you if it's מום mum but anyway
two is a מום. mum. שלוש אינו מום shalosh eino mum three
is not, so you see you said you needed it to be
here actually oh actually this is more lenient right because no this
is more strict. It's only a blemish if it has one fewer
vertebrae than you said. So here we see that it's a blemish
is one and two, you said two and three. So הגמרא ha-gemara
says תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא. tiyuvta de-Rav Huna tiyuvta.
So that is a contradiction of רב הונא Rav Huna that said
that the amount was for a מום mum was three and four,
here we're saying it's two and three is the minimum. So הגמרא
ha-gemara says רב הונא מתניתין אטעייא. Rav Huna matnitin ateiya. רב הונא
Rav Huna
was was made to err because of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה
Mishnah misled him or he was misled by the משנה. Mishnah. אי
סבר מדרישא
בגדי ei savar mi-reisha be-gedi the משנה Mishnah says that if it
doesn't have three vertebrae it's a מום, mum, so he figured what
animal are we talking about? Since originally we were talking about about
a goat because it talked about the ear folded over, סיפא נמי
בגדי seifa nami be-gedi the end is also about a goat. ולא
היא ve-lo hi it's not true. רישא בגדי וסיפא בטלה reisha be-gedi
ve-seifa be-taleh the beginning was a goat and the end we're talking
about a sheep. When we say explicitly goat we mean goat, otherwise
the default is sheep. So anyway that's where he got his mistake,
not obvious at all. Now you understand why he made a very
a very honest mistake. All right, moving on. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina
ben Antignos says notice again you know it's the more obscure תנאים
Tannaim that we're coming across. יבלת בעיניו yavelet be-einav that something has
a יבלת yavelet which is some type of like a like a
growth that protrudes coming out of its eye. ושניפגם עצם ידו ורגלו
ve-shenifgam etzem yado ve-raglo
or its arm or leg was nicked. Before we spoke about broken,
so here ושניפרק עצמו של פיו ve-shenifrak atzmo shel piv
or if the bone of the mouth was was was loosened or
taken off. What does that mean? רש"י Rashi says it means the
gums. So the gums, you know before we spoke about about a
tooth, you would think gums is a bigger מום, mum, but gums
are more hidden, they're basically completely hidden by by the lips. So
therefore by the gums it's not enough of a small injury, it
basically has to be you know taken out or detached I think
is a better word. And those would be a מום. mum. That's
his statement. Not clear if anybody argues on that, we'll see about
that in the גמרא. Gemara. עינו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה eino achat
gedola ve-achat ketana
now Michael was asking about this yesterday. Yesterday we talked about about
misshapen you know disproportionate limbs but we only talked about it in
terms of the thigh or the shoulder. Here we're talking about all
a range of limbs. One eye is big or one eye is
too small. אזנו אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה ozno achat gedola ve-achat ketana
or one is bigger than normal one is smaller. במראה be-mareh now
that's only if it's visibly different. ולא במידה ve-lo be-mida you don't
go take out a ruler and you decide oh this is 2.8
inches and this is 2.9 inches. Okay, that's not enough to be
enough of a difference and enough of a deformity. But if it's
visibly different sizes that is a מום. mum. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehuda omer שתי ביצים shtei beitzim if it's when we're back to
now the testicles.
אחת גדולה כשתיים שבחברתה achat gedola ki-shtayim she-be-chavertah if one is twice
as big as the other that is also a
מום. mum. ולא הודו חכמים ve-lo hodu chachamim they
didn't agree because again that is less visible although you
You know, we're talking about, no, not talking about what it looks,
the scrotum, we're talking about the actual testicles. Okay, not that the
scrotum itself is deformed, presumably that he might agree to. למימרא *Lememra*,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, this seems to say, דיבלת הוי
מומא *di-yabeles havei muma*, this יבלת *yabeles* which is again some type
of a like of a growth that it comes out of the
body, that's a blemish. ורמינהו *U-reminhu*, I'll ask you on this. ואלו
ששוחטים עליהם לא במקדש ולא במדינה *Ve-eilu she-shochtim aleihem lo ba-mikdash ve-lo
ba-medinah*, and now we are going to get and we're going to
see this in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* on the next דף daf,
*daf*, today's דף *daf* actually, hopefully we get to it, that the
exact category of something that falls midpoint. It's not enough of a
מום mum *mum* that you can שחט shacht *shecht* it outside the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, but it's a big enough problem
that you can't bring it as a קרבן korban *korban*. It's not
תמים tamim *tamim*, but it's not a מום mum? *mum*, okay, and
it falls right in the middle. So it's the worst-case scenario. And
here it says here are those that fall into that category. בעל
גרב garav, ובעל יבלת *Baal gerev u-baal yabeles*, if it has these
types of scabs or a יבלת *yabeles* again some type of a
protrusion of a growth of skin, that these are midpoint, that these
you can't bring as a קרבן korban. *korban* but you can שחט
shacht *shecht*. So how does our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* say that a
יבלת *yabeles* is a מום mum *mum* that you can שחט shecht
*shecht* on the basis of it? So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, רתסברא *Ra-tisbra*, one minute, let me even ask you before you
know if that whole thing makes sense. והא כתיב *Ve-ha ksiv*, it's
explicit in the פסוקים pesukim *psukim* that a יבלת *yabeles* is a
blemish. And again here we are borrowing,
conflating from בכור bechor *Bechor* and other קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos*. What does
it say in the תורה Torah *Torah*? יבלת *Yabeles*, it says או
גרב garav, או יבלת *o garav o yabeles*, right, it says explicitly
גרב garav *garav* and a יבלת *yabeles* are a blemish. So so
now we got a problem. The משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* later says it's
only midpoint, but we have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that says it's
a complete blemish. And our משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says it's a blemish
when you have it on the eye. So let's take a look.
Eye is a blemish also.
Well that's exactly what we're going to see. Let's take a look.
אלא לא קשיא *Ela lo kashya*, so we're going to try a
couple of answers. הא בגופא הא בעינא *Ha be-gufa ha be-eina*. First
of all, difference between the body and the eye. In the eye,
it's much more visible, it looks it's much more disfiguring, so the
eye it's a blemish, that's our משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*, that's the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*, where it's only a midpoint, not a full blemish but
not perfect, that is on the rest of the body.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I still think there should be
a problem because if it's a growth it's visible.
Okay, so let's take a look, Michael, all the things you're going
to have I'm sure are in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. מכדי
*Michdi*, one minute, קרא סתם כתיב *kra stam ksiv*, the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says without any distinction that it's a מום mum *mum*. How
can you say the whole פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is only talking about
the eye? מה לי בגופא מה לי בעינא *Ma li be-gufa ma
li be-eina*, what difference does it make if the body or the
eye? The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says straight that יבלת *yabeles* is a
מום mum *mum*. אלא לא קשיא *Ela lo kashya*, so that's difficult.
הא דאית ביה עצם הא דלית ביה עצם *Ha de-is bei etzem
ha de-leis bei etzem*. So it's whether there's a bone in it
or there's not. If it's not a bone in it, then it's
just like a skin flap. A skin flap is no big deal.
But if it actually is some protrusion of skin and bone,
then that obviously is some real disfigurement.
Bone in the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* too, יבלת בעינו *yabeles be-eino* means
there's a bone?
Well let's take a look.
Okay, so let's take a look. דקרא *De-kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that says it's always a problem, דאית ביה עצם *de-is bei etzem*,
has a bone. מתניתין *Masnisin*, דלית ביה עצם *de-leis bei etzem*, our
two משניות *Mishnayos* is it's just a skin flap without a bone.
So and there it makes a difference, eye or the rest of
the body. בעינו *Be-eino*, in the eye, which is our משנה Mishna
*Mishnah*, הוי מומא *havei muma*, that's very disfiguring even if it's just
a skin flap. בגופא *Be-gufa*, in the body, לא הוי מומא *lo
havei muma*, it's not a blemish and that's the next משנה Mishna
*Mishnah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
one minute, that's very nice, but if it's all it is is
a skin flap, then I would question if it's a problem at
all. דלית לה עצם *De-leis la etzem*, if it has no bone,
בגופא פסולה *be-gufa psula*, it would be a problem in the body?
I mean yes, I admit in the eye it would be very
disfiguring, but if you just had a skin flap on the rest
of the body without would that you actually call a blemish? הרי
harei טילטול בעלמא הוא *Harei tiltul be-alma hu*, it's just like a
little skin flap, what's the big deal? Which again raises the question
all along, which is you know how do you define perfect, how
do you define blemish, how disfiguring, what are your, you know, not
only what's your range of like normal, which is a question, but
also like what types of things do you even pay attention to,
you know? I mean you don't say if the color is a
little bit off it's a מום mum. *mum*, right? So I mean
what types of things are considered significant enough or disfiguring enough?
So anyway here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, a יבלת *yabeles* is a
wart. Wart, okay. A wart is very different than a skin flap.
Well I said like a skin protrusion, but yeah, a wart.
A wart is colored, right,
often textured disfiguration. Uh-huh. Skin flap I would think is
a piece
of skin that
covers that like protrudes and whatever. Also you have a bone in
a wart? I mean I don't know if you have a bone
in a skin flap either. No, yeah. I don't know, it's obviously
some protrusion of skin, okay, but the fact the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says without a bone, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* calls it like a
skin flap, that's what a טילטול *tiltul* is. So that's why I've
been calling it that.
What happens to this animal that it's not the one that's not
considered?
The same thing that happens with one that has no מום mum
*mum* at all, you have to wait till it gets a מום
mum? *mum* and until that point you can't do anything with it.
So they're trying to be strict even though the
תורה Torah *Torah* says if it has this
יבלת *yabeles*, whatever it is, right, they're trying to say no, no,
no, they're
not all יבלת *yabeles* are not all the same. Right.
"What is behind that?
Yeah I you know again I don't know
I mean because it makes things harder and a greater monetary loss
for the people.
Well I said it was too bad you weren't here yesterday where
we had a whole argument between Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri where Rabbi Akiva said
עד מתי אתה מכלה ממונם של ישראל. Ad matai ata mechaleh mamonam
shel Yisrael. So there is that attitude that is expressed. I you
know I don't know obviously on the other hand there's some things
that they call a מום mum that aren't mentioned at all in
the תורה Torah that you wouldn't have ever expected like a slightly
deformed toe or something. So I mean I'm not sure that's always
a question of just how much are your decisions informed by those
sort of you know the sort of practical implications and how much
are they by your conceptual models that you're bringing to it. Like
if this is just a flap so do you really call it
a מום? mum
You know so I mean it you know those issues about what
are how does this affect real people you know is part of
the decision making process which came up yesterday with Rabbi Akiva and
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri but I'm just saying I think that they're
also trying to have a sense of honesty to what they think
you know conceptually a מום mum is about and something that's so
trivial like a flap you know on the other hand like I
said there are things that aren't in the פסוקים psukim, at all
that they said are מומים. mumim. So I'm not sure you can
sort of determine a consistent pattern about that. All right so let's
see so
the
גמרא Gemara says like this back to where we are.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara. says תילתולא באדם מהו דתנן רבי אליעזר
אומר בעלי התילתולין פסולין באדם וכשרים בבהמה. Tiltula b'adam mahu detnan Rabbi
Eliezer omer ba'alei hatiltulin pesulin b'adam u'ksherim b'vehemah. People with skin flaps
is a problem for כהנים kohanim but it's not good but for
animals it's totally not problematic. So this also a question raised yesterday
right? What standard do כהנים kohanim go by? And here
you see we have had two standards right? One was enough of
a מום mum? that you would שחט shecht a קרבן korban outside
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, the other was a big enough problem not
to bring it as a קרבן. korban And here we see that
the כהנים kohanim standard is even higher than that that even something
that the animal would be totally כשר kasher with would be a
problem for a כהן kohen because by there it's much less about
the way the גמרא Gemara, frames it by a כהן kohen it's
much less about the idea of מום mum and much more about
the idea of like within a certain limited band of quote unquote
normalcy שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon.
So even if you can't even call it a blemish you know
that is more closer to what the גמרא's Gemara idea before was
about תמים tamim by the animal. So here you have the כהנים
kohanim have even a higher standard even than just an animal bringing
as a קרבן korban let alone a מום. mum Anyway you see
that it's okay by a קרבן korban. so how could you say
that's a problem? אלא אידי ואידי בעיניו. Ela idi v'idi b'einav. Okay
fine it's both about the eye. ולא קשיא הא בשחור הא בלבן
V'lo kashya ha b'shachor ha b'lavan that when is it a when
does the תורה Torah say it's a problem or
let me again the תורה Torah still that it has a bone.
When in our משנה Mishna is it a what is the difference
about whether it is or is not a problem? It's they both
could be in the eye which is more disfiguring but the difference
is whether it's the black of the eye or the white of
the eye. So the גמרא Gemara says and the white of the
eye as we said before is less of a problem. והא אין
מומין בלבן? V'ha ein mumim b'lavan? One minute presumably there are no
blemishes in the white of the eye which is again so bizarre
right? I mean it's disfiguring why shouldn't it be a problem? Why
is the eye special that the white of the eye is excluded?
And that's the issue we raised before. I mean you know there
by the eye it particularly focuses on a particular מום mum. that
the תורה Torah mentions by an eye תבלול בעינו tavlul b'eino and
wants to define it very narrowly. What is precisely defined as the
eye? But why isn't it part of a more generic category of
disfiguring things?
Anyway yeah is it because the white of the eye can often
have a marking and maybe they just assume it could be more
natural?
Maybe but this isn't a mark it's a skin flap and the
גמרא Gemara sort of takes a categorical approach אין מומין בלבן. ein
mumim b'lavan. Okay now the question is how we read the next
line whether the גמרא Gemara steps back from that. So here's what
the גמרא Gemara says. So again the תורה's Torah case is that
there's a bone in it. How comes our משנה's Mishna. distinguish between
whether these flaps are or are not a full מום? mum אלא
אידי ואידי Ela idi v'idi now תוספות Tosafot is
here it says בלבן b'lavan but תוספות's Tosafot גירסא girsa is בשחור
b'shachor because תוספות Tosafot wants to be consistent with the statement before
that the white is never a problem. So תוספות Tosafot reads it
you're right they're both in the black of the eye. ואמר ריש
לקיש לא קשיא הא דאית ביה שיער הא דלית ביה שיער. V'amar
Reish Lakish lo kashya ha d'it bei se'ar ha d'leit bei se'ar.
Is there hair growing out of this skin in as there's a
piece of skin I don't know how skin grows out of the
eye altogether okay so
and then hair grows out of that. And then hair grows out
of that. I don't right I don't get it at all but
that's really disfiguring. Anyway that's what תוספות Tosafot reads. רש״י Rashi reads
that it's like our גירסא girsa it's in the white. So according
to רש״י Rashi this principle that there is no מום mum, in
the white of the eye is at least not completely categorical.
Okay yes so תוספות's Tosafot case is that there is a flap
in the eye and then in some there's hair growing out of
it? If there's just hair if there's just a flap going out
of the black that's not a problem?
It's not you can't bring it as a קרבן korban but it's
not a מום mum to שחט shecht on." "Scheindels" The speaker says
"Scheindels" (likely a name or reference). "Gedi" (kid goat). "Ozen" (ear). "Shtei
atzamot" (two bones). "Tiltula" (flap/growth). "Ba'alei hatiltulin" (those with flaps). "Pesulin" (invalid).
"U'ksherim b'vehemah" (and valid in an animal). "Shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon" (equal
among the descendants of Aaron). "Tavlul b'eino" (a cataract/spot in the eye).
"Girsa" (version/textual variant). "Ha d'it bei se'ar ha d'leit bei se'ar" (this
one has hair in it, this one does not have hair in
it). "Scheindels" שיינדלס. Scheindels. "Gedi" גדי. gedi. "Ozen" אוזן. ozen. "Shtei atzamot"
שתי עצמות. shtei atzamot. "Tiltula" תילתולא. tiltula. "Ba'alei hatiltulin" בעלי התילתולין. ba'alei
hatiltulin. "Pesulin" פסולין. pesulin. "U'ksherim b'vehemah" וכשרים בבהמה. u'ksherim b'vehemah. "Shaveh b'zaro
shel Aharon" שוה בזרעו של אהרן. shaveh b'zaro shel Aharon. "Tavlul b'eino"
תבלול בעינו. tavlul b'eino. "Girsa" גירסא. girsa. "Ha d'it bei se'ar ha
d'leit bei se'ar" הא דאית ביה שיער הא דלית ביה שיער. ha
d'it bei se'ar ha d'leit bei se'ar.
"What is behind that? Yeah I you know again I don't know
I mean because it makes things harder
and a greater monetary loss for the people. Well I said it
was too bad you
weren't here yesterday where we had a whole argument between Rabbi Akiva
and Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri where Rabbi Akiva said עד מתי אתה
מכלה ממונם של ישראל. So there is that attitude that is expressed.
I you know I don't know obviously on the other hand there's
some things that they call a מום mum. that aren't mentioned at
all in the תורה Torah. that you wouldn't have ever expected like
a slightly deformed toe or something. So I mean I'm not sure
that's always a question of just how much are your decisions informed
I don't know, I don't know, I cannot be sure. These are
all questions of how bad it is, but I don't get it.
רש״י's Rashi גרסא girsa is better at least because I don't know
why the white should be categorically excluded. But I also don't understand
how you can get skin growing out of an eye. Anyway, at
least the way I understand maybe it kind of goes to the
side a little bit too much because the edge of the white.
Yeah, so you mean whether it gets into the eye but it
comes from outside? Maybe, yes. Charlie? So there are certain types of
tumors that grow on the eye. Oh, that's interesting. They're not very
common but I just looked it up.
Oh wow, I've never heard of that. Wow.
They even occur in humans too.
Wow. Does hair ever come out of them?
I
don't know, possibly.
All right. Okay, let's move on. אחת גדולה. Achat gedola. תניא, Tanya,
גדולה, gedola, כשל עגל, keshel egel, if it's as big as that
of a cow that would be a problem if this is happening
in a sheep, or קטנה, ketana, if it's as small כשל אווז,
keshel avaz, like a duck. Either that would be too big or
too small. Now I want to say by the way that that's
not necessarily פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna seems
to mean אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה achat gedola ve'achat ketana means that
they're right disproportionate to one another, whereas the משנה, Mishnah. the ברייתא
braita seems to be reading it as if one is either bigger
than normal or smaller than normal and then wants to say how
big is considered too big and how small is considered too small.
Yes, Charlie? Charlie, what do you want to say?
It is the most common tumor in bovines.
Oh, look at that. What, that something in the eye?
Ocular melanoma.
And what happens? It's like actually like some skin is protrudes?
It is
a plaque, a small circular white elevation on the surface of the
eye.
Wow. Well, that might sound like the גמרא Gemara before about the
white spot that
the גמרא Gemara talked about. A squamous cell carcinoma is a hard
raised growth on the eyelids as opposed to the eye
itself.
Interesting. A papilloma, a wart-like growth. Oh, wart-like.
We need a vet in this.
Yeah, all right.
No, we do. Does anybody know of a guy?
Actually, my sister-in-law is a vet.
That's just the thing I'm doing.
Right, right. I agree with you.
Who's the vet? David Bessler.
Get him in here. Where is he?
He goes
to Chabad.
Okay. All right. Okay, וייטער. veiter. Okay, אוזן אחת גדולה, ozen achat
gedola, misshaped ears. רבנן עד כמה? Rabanan ad kama? So now we're
going on the point about the testicles where it was two-in-one ratio
was not enough for the Rabbis. So at what stage would the
Rabbis admit that it actually would be a מום? mum, תניא אחי
מומים אפילו אינו לשנייה אלא כפול כשרה, Tanya achei mumim afilu eino
lashniya ela kefol keshera, even if the second testicle is only as
small as like a bean that would still not be a problem,
so maybe they would not say it was a מום mum, at
all if they are misshapen.
But again, what's the Rabbis' position?
They disagreed with the fact one side was two to one, the
size of the testicles, it was a מום mum, and the Rabbis
disagreed.
So and they're saying?
They're saying presumably it doesn't matter how small it is. Okay, let's
take a look next משנה. Mishnah Just a very quick question.
When we said with the eyes, so are we saying that if
they're disproportionate then it's not a problem? And if they're both really
small?
I understand what you're saying. The משנה Mishnah sounds like one thing,
the גמרא Gemara sounds like another. I don't, how do we פסקן?
pasken? I don't know.
No, I mean both are small like a duck.
I understand, I understand. I think that makes a difference between the
way the משנה Mishnah read it and the ברייתא braita in the
גמרא. Gemara The משנה Mishnah sounds like it means disproportionate to one
another and the גמרא, Gemara. ברייתא braita in the גמרא Gemara sounds
like it means smaller than an average. So I don't know the
answer to that.
You mean the one is still?
I understood, I understood the question. Let's take a look at the
next משנה. Mishnah זנב העגל שאינו מגיע לערכוב. zenav ha'egel she'eino magia
la'arkov. Now if you have the tail of a calf that does
not reach the ערכוב, arkov, which we'll see is like the knee.
אמרו חכמים כל מרבית עגלים כל כן. amru chachamim kol marbit agalim
kol ken. And now it's actually quite fascinating because now they actually
talk about the norm of distribution. And they say this is the
norm of all of like the calves. כל זמן שהם מגדילות הן
נמתחות, kol zman shehem magdilot hen nimtachot, as long as
they grow, the tail continues to stretch out. But presumably the way
רש״י Rashi at least reads it is that they're not disagreeing, they're
agreeing. They're saying that it starts as long as getting up to
the knee joint and then it continues to grow. But and so
therefore anything that's not within that normal range would be a מום.
mum, So רש״י Rashi reads it as an agreement, not a
disagreement. איזהו ערכוב? eizehu arkov? What's the
ערכוב? arkov? שאמרו, she'amru, רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben
Antignos omer, בערכוב שב אמצע הירך, ba'arkov shebe'emtza hayerech, the knee in
the middle of the joint, which is basically what we'd call the
knee as opposed to the cows have one closer to the foot,
which for us would be the ankle, for them it's a little
higher up. But anyway we're talking about the knee. תניא, Tanya, finally
top of today's actual official דף, כף העליון ולא כף התחתון, kaf
ha'elyon velo kaf hatachton, the upper joint and not the lower joint.
וכנגדו בגמל ניכר, vekenegdo begamal nikar, and by camels in particular you
really see where the leg is jointed in that area. When we
were learning חולין Chullin we had a picture of that and you
can really see it by camels. Okay, but we're moving on. על
אלו מומים שוחטין את הבכור. al elu mumim shochtin et habechor. Now
we have a nice wrap-up משנה. Mishnah On all the מומים mumim
we mentioned before you can שחט shecht the בכור bechor, and ופסולי
המוקדשין נפדין עליהם. ufsulei hamukdashin nifdin aleihem. If it happened by קרבנות,
korbanot it's enough of a מום mum? to redeem it. So this
משנה Mishnah basically says there's really they're really all the same, the
definition of the מום, mum? which has been implicit, but it does
raise questions at the beginning of the פרק perek because of the...
at the beginning the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* when it tried to decide
what was a מום mum *mum*, focused on the פסוקים psukim? *pesukim*
about בכור bechor. *bechor* and ignored the and basically did not pay
any attention to the פסוקים psukim *pesukim* about the other קרבנות *korbanot*
which were much more detailed. So it's quite interesting why the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* all along has been ignoring the פסוקים psukim *pesukim* primarily,
mostly ignoring the פסוקים psukim *pesukim* that exist by the other קדשים
*kodshim* since here it seems to be putting them all in the
same category. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara: *Gemara*. הא
תו למה לי *Ha tu lamma li*? Why do I need this
wrap-up משנה Mishnah *mishna*? הא תנא tanna ליה רישא *Ha tana lei
reisha*, we already learned in the beginning, על אלו מומים mumim שוחטין
את הבכור *al elu mumin shochtin et habechor*, that's how our משנה
Mishnah, *mishna* begins. These are the blemishes you שוחט *shecht* a בכור
bechor, *bechor*. No, סיפא איצטריך *seifa istreich*, ופסולי המוקדשין נפדין עליהם *u'psulei
hamukdashin nifdin aleihem*. No, to tell you exactly what we've been saying,
that it's the same הלכה halacha *halacha* for בכור bechor *bechor* and
for other קרבנות *korbanot*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הא נמי
פשיטא *ha nami peshita*, that's also obvious. מדשחטינן מיפרק מיבעיא *Mid'shachtinan mifrak
mibaya*? If you can שוחט *shecht* without redeeming, right, that's the big
חידוש *chiddush* of a בכור bechor *bechor*, that with a מום mum
*mum* you can שוחט *shecht* even though it has the same קדושה
kedusha *kedusha*. So of course you could redeem by another קרבן korban
*korban*. Now again, that's only obvious if you assume that they're basically
the same category, right? I mean, the Torah says one thing by
a בכור bechor *bechor* and another thing by קרבנות *korbanot*, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here takes it for granted that the same concept
of מום mum, *mum* should apply to both. Okay, so again, it
would have been very interesting though to explore more directly the פסוקים
psukim *pesukim* it says by the other קרבנות *korbanot*, which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* has not really done anyway. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says it's obvious it's the same הלכה halakhic *halacha*, אלא איידי דתנא
שלוש הוסיף *ella eidi detana shalosh hosif*, since we said yesterday, right,
that אילא *Ila* added three other מומים mumim. *mumim*, ואמרו לו לא
שמענו *ve'amru lo lo shamanu*, and the rabbis said we don't have
a tradition about this, לא שמענו את אלו *lo shamanu et elu*,
וקתני וסיפא יחידאי *u'ktani ve'seifa yechida'ei*, and then afterwards we have some
משניות *mishnayot* that are said in the name of individual opinions, רבי
חנינא בן אנטיגנוס *Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos*, even though we don't have
explicitly mentioned a debate, דקא סתמי בכולהו *dekasasmei bekulhu*, על אלו מומים
שוחטין את הבכור ופסולי המוקדשין נפדין עליהם *al elu mumin shochtin et
habechor u'psulei hamukdashin nifdin aleihem*. That's why we have this wrap-up to
tell you that even though some other opinions were mentioned as individual
opinions, really we all agree about it all, other than that one
little debate we had before, which even then we said that the
later בית דין *beis din* came around to his position. So really
therefore to tell you that all of these positions are really consensus.
Again, except for the explicit ones which are mentioned in the debates.
But even the ones that are mentioned in the name of individual
opinions are really the consensus. Okay, and now we move to this
interesting middle category where it's enough of a problem not to bring
it as a קרבן korban *korban*, but not enough of a problem
to שוחט *shecht* on it. ואלו שאין שוחטין עליהם לא במקדש ולא
במדינה *Ve'elu she'ein shochtin aleihem lo bamigdash velo bamedinah*. You can't שוחט
*shecht* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, it's not perfect
enough to שוחט *shecht* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*,
but it's not enough of a מום mum *mum* to שוחט *shecht*
outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. And now some of
these are variations of what we said before and some of them
are totally new categories. Let's take a look. חברור והמים שאין קבועים
*Chavarur vehamayim she'ein kevuim*. So there's חברור *chavarur*, this like white, what
was that again, white spots and water that is not fixed, meaning
right now it has this problem but it is not seen as
permanent. And really that can be generalized, right, רש"י *Rashi* said white
spots in the eye. That really can be generalized to any מום
mum. עובר *mum over*, right, any transitory blemish. You can't שוחט *shecht*
on the basis of it, but while it has the blemish, you
can't bring it as a קרבן korban. *korban*. Okay, so a transitory
blemish puts you right in the middle. You can't bring it and
you can't שוחט *shecht*. והחטין הפנימיות שנפגמו אבל לא נעקרו *Vehachitin hapnimiyot
shenifgemu aval lo ne'ekru*. The inner molars that were, or the roots
of the molars that were damaged or nicked, but they weren't completely
uprooted. Now that's interesting because presumably we said where they were those
damages on the inner molars, they were not visible. If they're not
visible, so again, is this a definition of תמים *tamim*, that it
doesn't have to be a מום mum *mum*, it's enough of a
problem that it's not תמים *tamim*? It's a different standard by bringing
it as a קרבן korban. *korban*, not just the absence of מום
mum, *mum*. Or is it a different standard of what visible means?
Maybe under certain circumstances it's visible and maybe it's a different standard
when it comes to bringing it as a קרבן korban, *korban*. ובעל
גרב garav ובעל יבלת *U'vaal garav u'vaal yabbelet*, this is what we
quoted before, different types of scabs or warts or skin flaps. ובעל
חזזית chazazis? *U'vaal chazazit*, another type of a wart. All of those
are not perfect enough as a קרבן *korban*, but they're not a
big enough problem to be a מום mum, *mum*. Okay, and we
said that that was on the body, not on the eye. Now
we get a totally different category. Not things about physical deformities, but
just about things about how appropriate is it to be brought as
a קרבן *korban*. זקן *Zaken*, if it's very old, וחולה *vecholeh*, or
it's sick, ומזוהם *u'mezoham*, it's smelly. Yeah, well these come up very
regularly. ושנעבדה בו עבירה v'shene'evda bo aveira *U'shene'evda bo aveirah*, a sin
was done with it, which means it was an act of bestiality.
ושהמית אדם *Veshehimit adam*, or it killed somebody, it gored somebody. And
the last two is על פי עד אחד או על פי בעלים
*al pi ed echad o al pi ba'alim*, that you only have
one witness or the owner's test admits to it. Why? Because if
you have two witnesses, then you put the animal to death and
they're forbidden in benefit. So you don't even have to say that
they're not a קרבן *korban*. You only have the animal around if
you only have one witness. Exactly, but if you only have one
witness or the owner, you're actually allowed to שוחט *shecht* it and
get benefit from it, but you cannot use it as a קרבן
*korban*. וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס *Vetumtum ve'androgynos*. And if it has a טומטום tumtum
*tumtum*, which is that it has both, the טומטום tumtum *tumtum* is
that the genitalia are covered up, and an אנדרוגינוס androgynous, *androgynos* is
androgynous, so it has male... לא במקדש ולא במדינה, it's just repeating
the point, these you cannot שחט shecht, outside the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash. but you can't שחט shecht in the בית המקדש, it's not
perfect enough, but it's not a מום mum, enough that you can
שחט shecht it outside. רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer, side switch,
it's—Rabbi Yishmael says אין לך מום גדול מזה. ein l'cha mum gadol
mizeh. If it's an אנדרוגינוס, androgynous, טומטום we'll discuss, but at least
an אנדרוגינוס, androgynous there's no bigger blemish than this. Meaning, if it
is a male, which is what it would have to be by
a בכור, bechor and it still has also genitalia of a female,
that is a big enough deformity
that that's a מום. mum, Okay, so that's what he says. וחכמים
אומרים, v'chachamim omrim, אינו בכור אלא נגזז ונעבד. eino bechor ela nigzaz
v'ne'evad. They're even more lenient. They say it's not a בכור. bechor
You know why? Because it's not a male. And then they're not
necessarily saying it's a female, maybe it's a third category. Okay, what
it's not—and actually somebody just told me that I have a friend
who's an optometrist and, you know, and he sees a lot of
people. And anyway, so one person came in who actually was transgendered
and, you know, so she—so she was born a he, now's a
she, but on his—on his form that he has to fill out,
he has male, female, and other. And he actually—he said he actually
had to check other. So anyway, so this is—I mean, I'm serious
about this, that people that are into, you know, gender identity very
like the idea that the גמרא spends time discussing אנדרוגינוס androgynos. and
the possibility of a third gender. So anyway, he's transgendered? What are
you trying to say? So born a man is now—right, but when
that man became a woman, that's when the person checked other? Well,
he was—she was, I think she was pre-op. She hadn't—but it doesn't
matter because from a medical perspective he had to know that this
person was taking all these hormones or whatever in order to maintain
this appearance, so it was important just medically to understand that. I
mean, he calls her
she, you know, treated whatever gender she wanted to identify with, but
from the medical perspective he had to know.
Anyway, he calls himself a third category. Well, some do, definitely, right,
exactly. So there's like interesting gender politics around this. But let me
just spell out what the debate was—is. So the first opinion says
it's a male or possibly a male but not definitely a מום,
mum, so therefore you're in this middle category and can't do anything.
The second one says no, no, no, it's a male with a
מום, mum or at least even if it is a male, it's
definitely a מום, mum, and therefore you can שחט, shecht. it's a
male—if it's a male with a מום, mum but it still has
קדושת בכור kedushas bechor because it might be a male. And the
third one says it doesn't even have קדושת בכור, kedushas bechor, you
can shear it, you can work it, it's not a male, end
of story. Yes, Charlie. This is—the issue of transgender is a real
issue because there are Jews who have sex change operations. Right. And
I actually was at a מנין minyan with one recently. Yeah, there's
a lot of interesting הלכה halakhic, around this. Right. Okay, I'm not
going to get into this discussion, but that—all right, moving on. When
this—when this started—when I was a kid and this started happening, you
know, sex change operations, you know, we used to make jokes about
it,
oh, so could the person count for a מנין? minyan? Anyway, but
now these are real, real הלכות.
halachos. Yeah. All right, anyway, moving on. גרב וילפת. garav v'yallefes. So
we'll get to all that fun in a minute if you let
me get there. So גרב לא? garav lo? So you're telling me
that a wart is not a מום? mum, והכתיב גרב דאורייתא. v'hachasiv
garav d'Oraisa. The תורה Torah says גרב, garav whatever that is, some
type of a wart in the תורה. Torah, But we're dealing with
שפלה. shifla. Okay, so the גמרא says וחזזית לא? v'chazazis lo? And
a חזזית? chazazis. והכתיב ילפת דאורייתא. v'hachasiv yallefes d'Oraisa. It says ילפת,
yallefes, and we're going to say that ילפת yallefes is a חזזית.
chazazis. דתניא גרב זה החרס. d'tanya garav zeh hacheres. So when it
says גרב, garav that's חרס, cheres, which is some type of very
dry wart. ילפת זו חזזית מצרית. yallefes zu chazazis mitzris. And the
ילפת yallefes is the Egyptian חזזית. chazazis So you see the same
things in the תורה Torah are mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah. Why
are they not a מום? mum, ואמר ריש לקיש למה נקרא שמה
ילפת? v'amar Reish Lakish lama nikra shema yallefes? Why is it called
ילפת? yallefes? שמלפפת והולכת עד יום המיתה. shemelafefes v'holeches ad yom hamisa.
Because it like, you know, it sort of cleaves to you, it
licks on you, it adheres to you until the day of death,
not very pleasant. So anyway, you see these are really problematic. So
why does our משנה Mishnah. say they're not? So בשלמא חזזית אחזזית
לא קשיא כאן בחזזית המצרית כאן בחזזית דעלמא. bishlama chazazis achazazis lo
kashya kan b'chazazis hamitzris kan b'chazazis d'alma. חזזית chazazis isn't the problem
because חזזית chazazis. is our translation of the word ילפת yallefes in
the תורה, Torah's but that might be what we specifically called it,
which was the Egyptian חזזית. chazazis Maybe the חזזית in our משנה
Mishnah is less severe and therefore it's not a problem. אלא גרב
אגרב קשיא. ela garav agarav kashya. But you really do have a
problem. The תורה Torah says גרב garav. is a מום mum and
our משנה Mishnah says גרב garav is not an issue. So the
גמרא says גרב אגרב נמי לא קשיא הא בלח הא ביבש. garav
agarav nami lo kashya ha b'lach ha b'yavesh. The תורה's Torah, גרב
garav. where it's a מום mum. is dry, which is sort of
like really either disfiguring or really permanent, and ours is with a
moist one which presumably can heal. לח מיתסי, lach misassi, a moist
one will heal. יבש לא מיתסי, yavesh lo misassi, a dry one
won't heal. So therefore in our משנה Mishna it's not a problem
because it's not permanent. So the גמרא says ולח מיתסי? v'lach misassi?
A moist one can heal? והכתיב, v'hachasiv, it says, יככה ה' בשחין
מצרים ובעפולים ובגרב ובילפת. yakecha Hashem b'shchin Mitzrayim u'v'apolim u'v'garav u'v'yallefes. What—ובגרב
ובילפת. u'v'garav u'v'yallefes. ובילפת v'yalefet thank you ובילפת v'yalefet so anyway it
says it says there גרב garav and it says אשר לא תוכל
להרפא asher lo tuchal l'herafe it says ומדכתיב u'midichtiv ובחרס u'vacheres הרי
and it says one of the things mentioned number one is חרס
cheres which is the dry one. So and it also mentions in
that פסוק pasuk גרב. garav, So therefore if one type of the
wart is explicitly the dry one, גרב garav is לח, lach, is
moist, and it says אשר לא תוכל להרפא asher lo tuchal l'herafe
that it won't heal. So you see that even if it's moist
it won't heal. So how can you say our משנה's moist and
it will heal? So the גמרא says אימא eima וכמה v'chama אשר
לא תוכל להרפא asher lo tuchal l'herafe and it says it can't
heal. אלא תלתא הוי. ela tlata havei. There are three types of
גרב. garav דקרא יבש בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ. dikra yavesh bein mibifnim
bein mibachutz. When it's mentioned mentioned in the מומים that a גרב
garav, is a מום, mum, that's dry on the inside and the
outside, which can also alternatively be called חרס cheres because it's like
pottery, it's totally dry. דמתניתין dimatnisin our משנה which says it's in
a middle category, לח מבחוץ מבפנים lach mibachutz mibifnim is moist on
the inside and outside and therefore it can heal and therefore it's
in this category where you can't שחט shacht but you can't bring
as a קרבן. דמצרים, d'Mitzrayim, the one in the פסוק pasuk right
that says יככה ה' בשחין מצרים ובטחורים, yakecha Hashem b'shchin Mitzrayim u'vatchorim,
right? So the one that's mentioned in the context of the of
the afflictions of the Egyptians that it can't heal, יבש מבפנים ולח
מבחוץ. yavesh mibifnim v'lach mibachutz. It's dry on the outside and moist
on the inside and that also would be a מום mum. that
you can שחט shacht on because as you said it cannot heal.
And how do we know that it's moist on the outside? דכתיב,
dichsiv, I said the wrong side? Hard on the inside, moist on
the outside. I must have swapped the sides. Hard on the inside,
moist on the outside. That if it's that it could heal more
that way? The גמרא understands that if it's hard in the core
it's less it it won't heal as much. That's what I don't
know, that's what the גמרא understands. So anyway you would have thought
that the other way is more like more you know is more
infected, right? Yeah. All right. Anyway, but that's the way the גמרא
understands that that way it won't heal. And how do we know?
דכתיב dichsiv והיה השחין v'haya hashchin because it says by מצרים Mitzrayim
אבעבועות פורח באדם ובבהמה ava'buot poreach b'adam u'vabehema it says sprouting. So
sprouting means like stuff is coming out of it which means that
it's moist on the outside but that it's hard on the inside.
Something that has to sprout from the inside. Right. I got it.
Okay. Moving on. Either way, if it's hard on the inside it
won't heal, it's a מום. mum, If it's moist on the inside
and outside it could heal and that's our משנה where if it's
a temporary מום you don't bring it as a קרבן but you
don't שחט. shacht Now we get to the whole new category. So
let's take a look. Things that are not מומים. הזקן והחולה והמזוהם.
hazaken v'hacholeh v'hamzuham. The smelly and old and sick. Okay, these are
things which are not appropriate as a קרבן but not necessarily a
מום, maybe not in the תמים category. So now we're going to
learn where we learn this from. Wait, is that different than what
we just had for the משנה before? We're saying could we just
had also זקן חולה מזוהם. zaken choleh mzuham. We're quoting it. Now
for the גמרא. מנא הני מילי? minani mili? Where do I know
this from? דתניא רבנן, d'tanya rabanan, מן הצאן, min hatzon, it says
if a person brings a קרבן מן הצאן ומן הכבשים ומן העזים
יקריבו. min hatzon u'min hakvasim u'min haizim yikravu. From the sheep, from
from the flock, from the sheep, from the goats. So the from
from from is understood to be limiting. Not all, not everything you
would have brought, only a subset from them. So what are those
three limiting words throwing you?
פרט לזקן ולחולה ולמזוהם. prat l'zaken u'l'choleh u'l'mzuham.
So the three things are to exclude those three cases: old, sick,
and smelly. וצריכי, u'tzrichi, you need all three. דאי כתב רחמנא חד,
d'ee kasav rachmana chad, had it just said one, למעוטי זקן דלא
הדר ברי l'imutei zaken d'lo hadar bari being old, because that you
don't get better from being old. Like they said being old is
no fun but it's better than the alternative, right? So that's anyway
something that is a permanent condition. אבל חולה דהדר ברי, aval choleh
d'hadar bari, but if it's sick maybe it'll get better, maybe it's
not as bad. אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that wouldn't be excluded.
ואי כתב למעוטי חולה דלאו אורחיה, v'ee kasav l'imutei choleh d'lav orchai,
if it had just said another one, just or if it had
just indicated a sick, maybe sick because that's unusual. אבל זקן דהיינו
אורחיה, aval zaken d'hainu orchai, old which everything gets old, so
אימא לא, eima lo, maybe that would not be a problem. ואי
כתב רחמנא תרי, v'ee kasav rachmana trei, if it had just excluded
two, למעוטי הני דכחישי, l'imutei hani d'kachishi, both old and sick are
like weak. אבל מזוהם דלא כחיש, aval mzuham d'lo kachish, smelly which
isn't weak at least, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe it wouldn't be
excluded. ואינמי למעוטי מזוהם משום דמאיס v'einami l'imutei mzuham mishum d'mais or
the opposite, it would have excluded smelly because that's disgusting.
אבל הני דלא מאיסי, aval hani d'lo maisi,
these are not, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe it wouldn't
have been excluded.
וצריכי, u'tzrichi, so you needed to exclude all three because they all
have different characters to them. One doesn't get better, the other is
abnormal, the other is smelly. Okay, and now we get to the
category of things that are actually involved in an עבירה. aveira. ושנעבדה
בו עבירה was used in bestiality. מנא הני מילי? minani mili? דתניא
רבנן. d'tanya rabanan. So another פסוקים, psukim. not from the flock, but
the opening פסוק pasuk that about the עולה olah altogether. It says
אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן. adam
ki yakriv mikem korban min habehema min habakar u'min hatzon. From from
the animals, להוציא רובע ונרבע, l'hotzi roveia v'nirva, an animal used in
bestiality, whether the male or the female. מן הבקר, min habakar, להוציא
את הנעבד, l'hotzi es hane'evad, an animal that was worshipped as a
קרבן. ומן הצאן, u'min hatzon, or the sheep, להוציא את המוקצה, l'hotzi
es hamuktza, something which doesn't mean מוקצה muktza for שבת, Shabbos, set
aside for עבודה זרה avoda zara even if it's not actually worshipped.
ומן הצאן, u'min hatzon, the extra vav, להוציא את הנוגח, l'hotzi es
hanoge'ach, an animal that actually gored. Okay, so basically it adds to
our משנה *Mishnah* not just bestiality but even something that was used,
that was used in as an object of worship for עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah*. So let's take a look. So first of all the
גמרא *Gemara* says number one, הני בני קטלא נינהו *hani b'nei katla
ninhu*? You have to kill them and not the thing that was
worshipped, that's אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*, but but certainly the one that
gored or was used in bestiality, so what's the question about using
it as a קרבן *korban*? You're supposed to stone them. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says no, that's why we say על פי עד אחד
או על פי הבעלים *al pi eid echad o al pi habaalim*.
You only know it through one witness or through the or through
the owners and even though you know it as a fact, you
don't actually have it doesn't have the status of a שור הנסקל
*shor haniskal*. It's not just like it's a it's not just like
oh we can't prosecute but it really is אסור *assur*. If it
really was אסור *assur*, then I as the owner would eat it
if I knew that, you know once I know its real status.
It said it doesn't get that status unless you have a formal
court case with two witnesses. And therefore it never gets that הלכתי
*halachic* status of a שור הנסקל *shor haniskal*. Now we get onto
and that's all we're saying about that. Now we get onto what
everybody I think is more fascinated with which is the gender issues.
So let's take a look. Before we get there, can I just
ask something? Yes. Is the general outlook what is most pleasing to
God לרצון *leratzon*? Right. Or what human beings consider? Yeah, so I
have to tell you and I appreciate that you raised this. What
would we do without you רבקה *Rivka*? Because it's been bothering me,
you know this for I mean it always bothers me anyway when
we read it in, you know in the תורה Torah *Torah* in
אמור *Emor*, it's been bothering me throughout this פרק *perek*, is that
the whole idea of perfection, I mean it's really it's problematic and
particularly about the sense that perfection is defined by physical externals. You
know I mean you would think that in all this stuff around,
you know from a religious perspective, the whole point would be to
focus not on the externals, right? כי האדם יראה לעיניים והשם יראה
ללבב *ki ha'adam yireh la'einayim v'Hashem yireh lalevav*. You know and speaking
you know personally with two kids that are, you know that have
that are special needs and the whole
you know sense about
what's normal and not normal and you know attitudes towards inclusion and
exclusion, you know it's it's very it's very disturbing. I mean the
best that I can say is it's the same about the fact
that the תורה Torah *Torah*, you know why does the תורה Torah
*Torah* want our בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* to be gold and silver
and look so beautiful? I mean is that's not what true, you
know religious ideals are about or about that materialism. But you know
we know that people are influenced by externals and you know for
some people to create a sense of oh you know this represents
God or you know for some people would like דאווענינג *davening* in
like a שטיבל *shtiebel* and other people need their שול *shul* to
look a very particular way, the aesthetics, the decorum in order, you
know in order to imbue a certain type of a feeling or
a certain sense of awe. So you know I would say that
that's that's the way I understand it, a concession to human nature
and you know what people need in order to feel that this
gives them a sense of, you know something important and significant and
if God is a real God then we have to be very
careful of exactly what the animals look like. If we can give
him anything, even something that looks disgusting, then it lowers our estimation
of God. But in the end it's a concession to human nature.
That's the best I can understand, which you know still is a
problem because you know you have whenever you make these concessions, the
problem is okay you make a concession but how do you get
somebody to move beyond that also and to focus on the fact
that this is not really what is the you know essen- you
know what is most important and what is essential? You know I
mean you could say that that was a lot of the effort
of the of the נביאים *nevi'im* was trying to tell the people,
you know don't so pay so much attention to the קרבנות *korbanos*,
that's not what really matters, what matters more is how you treat
your you know your fellow human being and so on. So you
know I mean that's but but thank you for raising it because
it's definitely something that's been you know very troubling and especially you
get to like old and sick and are we supposed to care
for the old and sick, right? Well these are the ones you're
going to slaughter. What? I understand but I'm just saying you know
there's definitely a metaphor you're absolutely right that matters how you value.
I understand it's a yeah it's a and how about just the
whole issue about like you know physical deformities, right? And people that
are you know that are a little bit different than other people.
It's a real issue. There's an issue we didn't address is the
פנים *pnim*, I don't know if it will, like let's say the
animal is physically okay but you know has like some sort of
mental problem that like it can't go- no no no but like
it can't walk, you know right because it's bouncing off. Yeah I
don't know. We even test it like that. Right. What? Yeah I
don't know. What about most of these things have to do with
the more aesthetic and visibility other than the ones now that are
about עבירה *aveirah*. So it's possible that wouldn't be a problem. But
yeah it it definitely thank you it definitely really needed to be
said. It's been really bothering me the last few days. So let's
go on. The גמרא *Gemara* says like this, בשלמא טומטום במקדש לא
*bishlama tumtum b'mikdash lo*. So I understand why you the טומטום *tumtum*
is a problem, you can't bring it as a קרבן *korban* because
the טומטום *tumtum* is that the genitalia are covered up. It's a
male or female we just don't know. So I understand why you're
not going to bring it as a בכור bechor *bechor*, דילמא נקבה
היא dilma nekeivah hi, *dilma nekeivah hi*. ופדינו לא *u'fadino lo* and
don't shecht it outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, דילמא זכר zachar?
הוא *dilma zachar hu*. Maybe it's a female maybe it's a male
and maybe you could peel whatever it is that's blocking. You could
but you haven't and maybe it's a dangerous operation whatever it is.
Okay. So that I get. Okay. ולא הוי מומא *v'la havei muma*
and it's not a blemish. because it's covered, that presumably is not
enough of a problem to be a blemish. That's which is interesting,
why that is not enough of a disfigurement. But fine, I can
accept by the טומטום. But let's talk about the אנדרוגינוס. androgynous אלא
אנדרוגינוס, Ela androgynos, בשלמא במקדש לא, bishlama beMikdash lo, I understand you
don't bring it in the בית המקדש why as a בכור, bechor,
דילמא נקבה היא, maybe it's a female. אלא במדינה, Ela bemedina, but
outside the בית המקדש, either way, נהי נמי דזכר הוא, nehi nami
dezachar hu, if it was a male, תעשה נקבות חריץ, teasei nekeivus
charitz, let the female genitalia be like a crevice, okay, חריץ, charitz,
which is the crevice is a type of a מום, of וישחט
עליה. veyishchat aleha. So because one of the things that the תורה
Torah says is או חרוץ, o charutz, which is an animal which
has some type of a crevice in its body, unnatural one. So
אמר אביי אמר קרא, Amar Abaye amar kra, או חרוץ או שבור,
o charutz o shavur, creviced or broken. חרוץ דומיא דשבור, Charutz dumya
deshavur, מה שבור במקום עצם, ma shavur bemakom etzem, the same way
a break means a break at a bone, אף חרוץ במקום עצם,
af charutz bemakom etzem, it has to be in a place where
there is a bone and not in that area of the animal
where there is no bone. So therefore that's how it's possible that
we would not consider it a blemish. Again, the funny thing is,
even if it doesn't fit in the narrow definition of that word
in the תורה, Torah what about this generic category, you know, about
disfiguring things? We know. So which is obviously the second opinion in
the משנה, but here it's saying that no, that's not. Again, which
would make, you know, the idea of like this third gender, you
know, from the gender identity to be very happy, we're not calling
it a מום, right? It's something that's separate. But it's interesting, not
calling it either a separate gender, which is the last opinion in
the משנה. רבא אמר בלא שבור נמי לא מצי אמרת חרוץ במקום
בשר הוי מומא. Rava amar belo shavur nami lo matzi amart charutz
bemakom basar havei muma. Even without the comparison to broken, you could
not say that this problem of חרוץ charutz applies to a place
without a bone. Why? אי סלקא דעתך הוי מומא, Ei salka dachach
havei muma, were it to be a blemish, כיון דאמר גרב חרס,
keivan deamar garav cheres, we just said that גרב, which is a
מום, is this type of hardened, you know, pottery-like, whatever, dried, you
know, wart or something. מכדי חרוץ, Michdi charutz, that actually doesn't just
ride on the surface, that actually digs into the skin. דכתיב ומראהו
עמוק מן העור, dechsiv umareihu amok min haor, because it says by
the leprosy, by צרעת, tzaraas, that it's deeper than the skin, and
we say כמראה חמה העמוקה מן הצל, kemarei chamah haamukah min hatzel,
which is always a very funny phrase, like the sun looks deeper
than the shadows, we always assume the opposite, anyway, we're not going
to go there. Anyway, since it speaks about this type of a
חרס, cheres, we assume that that also digs in and gets into
the skin, and that's not a problem. So, I mean, and that's
a problem, but why then, so but why does it have to
say גרב separately if anytime something goes into the skin it's problematic?
I don't know. Somehow we're making some comparison to צרעת. tzaraas. ולכתוב
רחמנא חרוץ ולא בעי גרב, velichtov Rachmana charutz velo bei garav, so
why didn't the תורה Torah just say a crevice and not have
to say this case of the wart, since this type of a
wart would dig into the skin anyway? ואמינא חרוץ דלא מאיס הוי
מומא, vaamina charutz dela ma'is havei muma, if a normal crevice isn't
a blemish, is already a blemish, גרב דמאיס, garav dema'is, how much
more so would a גרב which A, digs into the skin and
number two is more disgusting, certainly would be a blemish. So כתב
רחמנא גרב למימרא דחרוץ במקום בשר לא הוי מומא. kasav Rachmana garav
lemeimra decharutz bemakom basar lo havei muma. So therefore you see from
the fact that the תורה Torah had to say גרב, that we
couldn't just infer that that was a problem because it dug into
the skin, that a crevice normally, unless it's in a place of
a bone, would not be a problem. Okay, so that was pretty
like, you know, sort of complicated, but the basic פשט pshat was
that normal this problem of חרוץ charutz was only in a place
where there's a bone, so you cannot normally say that just because
it has female genitalia that it falls into the category of חרוץ.
charutz. Now the גמרא goes on to the other opinions in the
משנה. רבי ישמעאל אומר אין לך מום גדול מזה. Rebbi Yishmael omer
ein lecha mum gadol mizeh. כאביי לא אמר. Ke-Abaye lo amar. Now
why does Rebbi Yishmael say that it is a מום, if we
just got through arguing why it wasn't? So he doesn't say like
Abaye, חרוץ דומיא דשבור לא אמרינן. charutz dumya deshavur lo amrinan. We
don't say חרוץ charutz has to be like broken. Broken is a
bone, crevice is anywhere. So therefore this female genitalia counts, constitutes חרוץ
charutz and therefore it's a blemish. כרבא למה לא אמר, Ke-Rava lamah
lo amar, he wasn't convinced by Rava's arguments. It was a little
anachronistic. Anyway, that would not have convinced him. Why? דילמא היכא דלא
מינכרא, dilma heicha dela minchara, that maybe that if it's in a
place where it's not obvious, then it's not, you know, then a
crevice wouldn't be an issue. אבל היכא דמינכרא מום רע קרינן ביה,
aval heicha deminchara mum ra karinan bei, and here it would be
more visible. Okay, so whatever it is, obviously it seems like Rebbi
Yishmael's position makes more sense, but if you're going to call it
a male, it certainly would be a מום for a male. Okay,
and that's his position, so either it is, we're going to go
further, you have to go, but I think we're going to go
a little further today, so we're going to hopefully catch up. Luckily
it's a short דף עמוד ב. daf amud beis. Okay, so he
basically says what makes sense. He is even if I'm willing to
consider it's a male, it's a male with a blemish, and therefore
you chuck it out of the בית המקדש. So בעי רבא. Bai
Rava. So רבא Rava asked: מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Ishmael? And when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says it's a blemish, what's
his reasoning? So it seems his reasoning is obvious, this genitalia is
a blemish. But no, here's the question we want to ask. מיפשט
פשיטא ליה Misha pshita lei is it obvious to him that אנדרוגינוס
בכור הוא ומומו עמו, androgynous bechor hu umumo imo, that an androgynous
is a male, meaning what does he think about the androgynous? Does
he think it's definitely a male but it's a male with this
female genitalia so it's a male with a blemish? או דילמא או
איספוקי מספקא ליה, O dilma u isfukei mesafke lei, he doesn't know
if it's male or female. And he says either way you can
eat it, right? Either it's female and then it's not a בכור
bechor, at all, or it's male with a blemish and then it's
a בכור bechor, with a blemish, right? ואם תמצא לומר, Ve'im timtza
lomar, and he's saying either way. אם תמצא לומר בכור הוא, Im
timtza lomar bechor hu, first of all maybe it's a female and
it's not a בכור bechor altogether. And even if it's a male,
הרי מומו עמו, harei mumo imo, it's got a blemish. Okay, so
you could—that's a reasonable position that maybe he says, you know, he's
uncertain whether it's male or female. So גמרא says: למאי נפקא מינה?
L'mai nafka mina? What do I care whether it's—either way you שחט
shacht it and eat it, what do I care whether he calls
it a—says it's a non-male or it's a male with a blemish?
So the גמרא says: Here's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. למילקי עליה
משום גיזה ועבודה. L'milkei alei mishum giza va'avoda. Number one is let's
say you don't שחט shachts it and you shear it or you
work it. So if you say it might be a female, you
can't give the guy lashes because maybe it wasn't a בכור bechor
altogether. If you say it's definitely a male with a מום, so
the מום lets you שחט shacht it, but it's still a בכור
bechor. and until you שחט it, if you shear it or work
it, you transgress. So would you be able to definitely know that
a person had violated? Is it a definite male and he definitely
violated or not? Here's a better נפקא מינה, nafka mina, a more
relevant: אינמי למיתביה לכהן. Inami l'misvei l'kohen. That's always the question. Do
I have to give it to a כהן? kohen? I had this
אנדרוגינוס androgynous animal born to me. If it's a definite male with
a מום, I have to give it to the כהן kohen and
the כהן kohen שחט it. But if it might be a female,
then I say you can't prove it's yours and therefore I get
to keep it and I get to שחט it and eat it.
So that's the big נפקא מינה nafka mina whether we say it's
a doubt or a definite male. Let's take a look. תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear. רבי אילעאי אומר משום רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Ilai omer mishum Rabbi Ishmael. רבי אילעאי Rabbi Ilai says in the
name of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. I was wondering whether this was
the same אילעא Ilai that we had in the משנה before. Remember
אילעא? Ilai? This is אילעאי. Ilai. How was his name spelled back
then? It was different, not with a י. yud. אילעא? Ila? Okay,
anyway, spelling sometimes changes. אילעאי. Ilai. No, we had רבי אילעאי Rabbi
Ilai before about the חמצה בר אילעאי. Hamza bar Ilai. Yeah, that's
true. That's יהודה בר אילעאי. Yehuda bar Ilai. That's yeah. So I
don't know. Okay, anyway, let's keep on going. רבי אילעאי אומר משום
רבי ישמעאל: Rabbi Ilai omer mishum Rabbi Ishmael: אנדרוגינוס בכור הוא ומומו
עמו. Androgynous bechor hu umumo imo. So here he's quoting רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael and it sounds like he's saying in a very definitive
term: It is a בכור bechor but it has a blemish. So
גמרא: שמע מינה מיפשט פשיטא ליה, Shma mina misha pshita lei, you
see it's obvious to him. So גמרא says: No, דילמא אם תמצא
לומר קאמר. dilma im timtza lomar ka'amar. Maybe he's saying even if
you say, even if you were to say it's a בכור, bechor
it has מומו עמו. mumo imo. But it doesn't mean we know
for sure that it's a בכור, bechor it doesn't mean we know
for sure that it's male. תא שמע: Ta shema: זכר ולא נקבה.
Zachar velo nekeva. It says by an עולה olah it has to
be male, so we say not female. כשהוא אומר למטה זכר, Keshehu
omer lemata zachar, and then it says again in the פסוק pasuk
male. שאין תלמוד לומר, She'ein talmud lomar, it didn't have to tell
me male, you've already told me that an עולה olah has to
be male. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar? Why does it say?
להוציא טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. Lehotzi tumtum ve'androgynous. To exclude טומטום and אנדרוגינוס androgynous
which are not fully male or definitely male. מאן? Man? Now who's
this going like? אילימא תנא קמא, Ileima tanna kamma, if it's our
first תנא of our משנה that said it's not a מום, but
nevertheless ספיקא הוא. sveika hu. He still says that an אנדרוגינוס androgynous.
is a doubt, right? And therefore you can't bring it as a
קרבן. It's not a מום but it's not necessarily male. ואתי קרא
למיעוטי ספיקא? Ve'ati kra l'imutei sveika? You wouldn't need a פסוק pasuk
to exclude a case of a doubt. Now why not? I mean
תוספות Tosafot says—usually תוספות Tosafot says of course, you know, you need
a פסוק to tell you how to deal with doubt. So תוספות
Tosafot says here's the difference. If it's a case that you—that might
come up from time to time and you—there might be a doubt
what the case is, then the תורה Torah might tell you here's
what you do in a case when you're not certain. But here
the question is not something that's different from time to time. It's
the category of אנדרוגינוס. androgynous? How do we treat the category of
אנדרוגינוס? androgynous, That's a הלכה halakhically question, that's not a fact question.
So the תורה might tell you what do you do in a
case where there's a factual doubt because we're human and we have
factual doubts. But if the question is about the הלכה, the legal
question of how do we define אנדרוגינוס, androgynous figure it out. I'm
not going to tell you, oh, if I God don't know whether
it's male or female and here's what you do because it's a
doubt, okay? So if—if you have a legal question if it's a
doubt, the תורה's not going to be addressing that legal question. So
therefore it's saying if it's according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma
that אנדרוגינוס androgynos is a doubt, so if that's true, the תורה
would not tell you, oh, because it's doubtfully הלכה how we categorize
it, don't treat it as a male. You figure out if
it's male or female and then you figure out which category it's
in.
The תורה would not have to tell you that.
Okay, so therefore it cannot be תנא קמא. tanna kamma. אלא רבנן
בתראי. Ella rabbanan batrai. How about the last רבנן? rabbanan? Remember the
last one said it's not—it's definitely not a בכור, bechor, right? It's
a—it's a ספק. safek. separate gender. So maybe they are the ones
that you needed the פסוק to exclude it based on זכר? zachar
So the גמרא says, no. מחדא קא נפקא? הא גבי בכור חד
קרא הוא דכתיב. me-chada ka nafka? ha gabei bechor chad kra hu
d'chtiv. Then one פסוק would have been enough. How do I know
one פסוק would have been enough? Because by בכור bechor it doesn't
say זכר zachar twice. By בכור bechor. it only says זכר zachar,
once. And nevertheless, we know, we have seen in the משנה that
there's an opinion that says אנדרוגינוס androgynos? is completely excluded from בכור.
It's not, it's a separate gender, it's not זכר, zachar it's completely
excluded. So if it were that opinion that even by בכור excludes
it completely, it's a completely separate gender, why by other קרבנות did
you need two פסוקים? psukim If by בכור we excluded it just
based on one זכר zachar, because it's not male. אלא פשיטא, Ella
peshita, it must be רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. It must be that
it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who says that it's a male with
a מום. אי אמרת בשלמא רבי ישמעאל מישרא פשיטא ליה, Ei amart
bishlama Rabbi Yishmael mishra peshita lei, if it's obvious to him that
it's a male with a מום, היינו דאיצטריך קרא למעוטי, hainu d'itztrich
kra l'mautei, then you understand why you needed the פסוקים psukim. to
exclude it. Because then I would have said, oh, well it is
male, it just has a blemish. So maybe even if I can't
bring it as a קרבן, maybe if I sanctify it, it has
קדושה and so on. So therefore you needed פסוקים psukim to tell
you, no, even though it's a male, because of this problem, it
doesn't have any קדושת קרבן kedushat korban if you try to sanctify
it. That's what I would say. אלא אי אמרת מספקא ליה, Ella
ei amart mesapka lei, but again, if it's possibly not even a
male, איצטריך קרא למעוטי ספיקא? itztrich kra l'mautei sefeika? Would you get
the point of why would I need the תורה to have addressed
it if it's just the issue of its doubtful status? So the
גמרא says, that so, anyway, that's so they were trying to prove
that according to, since you needed פסוקים psukim to exclude it, the
only reason you would need two פסוקים psukim to exclude it is
if it would have been a definite male with a blemish. And
the גמרא in the end rejects this and says, no, לעולם רבנן
בתראי, le'olam Rabbanan batrai, it really could be the latter רבנן Rabbanan
that says that it's a separate gender, וגבי בכור תרי קראי כתיבי,
v'gabei bechor trei krai ktivi, הזכר והזכרים. hazachar v'hazcharim. And even though
it's a separate gender, you need two פסוקים. psukim Okay, and it
does say two פסוקים by, by the end, anyway, about to wrap
up, by even by בכור it has two פסוקים. It says the
פסוק רש״י Rashi quotes, one is הזכר תקדיש hazachar takdish and אשר
יהיה לך הזכרים לה׳, asher yihiyeh lecha hazcharim l'Hashem, which means the
following: it might be a separate gender, but because it is a
separate gender, it's not necessarily excluded by one mention of the word
זכר, zachar right? Maybe זכר zachar is enough, you know, maybe זכר
zachar is only excluding the exact opposite gender, the female, but something
that's the middle gender maybe isn't excluded. Our only question was, was
that if you only needed one פסוק by בכור, why you needed
two פסוקים by the other animals to exclude the separate gender? And
our answer is, no, we have two פסוקים by בכור as well.
It says זכר zachar twice by בכור. So it could be it's
a separate gender, but one word זכר zachar might not be enough.
זכר zachar might only exclude female. You need the separate זכר to
exclude even this middle gender. Okay, so the upshot of all of
this was that we don't know according to the first position, does
it know if it's male or female? The second position says even
if it's male, it has a blemish. What we don't know is
whether that second position also has the doubt of whether it's male
or female or not, or would definitely call it a male with
a blemish, right? Or the third, or the third position says it's
a completely separate gender. And we're going to pick up on that
third position when we return. And again, the interesting point I think
that תוספות Tosafot makes, which is that the פסוקים would need to
tell you how you deal with a doubt in facts, but if
there's a doubt in law, then the פסוקים aren't going to tell
you how to deal with the fact that it is a doubt,
it'll either be one or the other and that's for you to
figure out. But we do have this remaining question about how do
we conceive of אנדרוגינוס? Do we have a doubt whether it's male
or female? Do we consider it to be a male with a
blemish? You could also say it's a female with a blemish, though
that possibility isn't being raised. I think it's because in general, and
I was also waiting for somebody to object to this, you know,
in general about comparing the whole idea of female genitalia to a
חריץ. charitz. You know, there's a very common way about thinking about
female as the non, the absence of male, right? As lacking male
genitalia. Thomas Laqueur, exactly. So I think it's for that reason, I
think it's for that reason that we don't consider it to be
a female with a מום. Once it has male genitalia, right, the
only, the possibility is, it can't be a female anymore because it
has male genitalia. But it's possible that it's a male with a
מום, and that's a possibility, or that it's a third gender. So
that we will continue with tomorrow. חזק חזק. Chazak chazak.